Guide to the Barlow Ware papers, 1921-2012.
Ware, Barlow papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Barlow Ware papers, 1921-2012.
4-3-2587
Barlow, Ware, 1925-2011.
5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, printed material, financial records, memorabilia.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Files of Barlow Ware relating to his life and work at Cornell University. Contains files from his work in the Office of Special Projects and Alumni Affairs. These files mostly pertain to fundraising for fraternities; several files contain copies of documents relating to the transfer of the houses to university ownership. Files relating to his personal life including many items regarding his family genealogy from the Ware, Barlow, Effinger families and others, correspondence with family members including many letters written to his mother, Katherine Taylor Effinger, as a child and photographs. Photo albums covering his entire life, including his time at Cornell as a student. Files relating to his support of Cornell include his awards and recognitions including his Hall of Fame and Foremost Benefactor inductions. Also a typescript European travel diary from a lengthy trip in 1956-1957. Also material relating to his support of the glass Blaschka Marine Invertebrate Collection. Other items relate to his work with Rotary International and the Boy Scouts of America.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
William Barlow Ware Jr. graduated from Cornell University in 1947. Ware served as manager to the wrestling team and as Touchdown the Bear. He would later join Cornell to work in Alumni Affairs and Development as director of Special Projects. He also served as the voice of the Big Red as the announcer at hockey and football games. His dedication to Cornell and the Ithaca community through his service and his donations would earn him numerous recognitions including induction into the Cornell Athletic Hall of Fame, recognition as a Foremost Benefactor, the Frank H. T. Rhodes Exemplary Alumni Service Award, Rotary Foundation Meritorious Service Award, Boy Scouts of America Silver Beaver Award, and many others.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Files of Barlow Ware relating to his life and work at Cornell University. Contains files from his work in the Office of Special Projects and Alumni Affairs. These files mostly pertain to fundraising for fraternities; several files contain copies of documents relating to the transfer of the houses to university ownership. Files relating to his personal life including many items regarding his family genealogy from the Ware, Barlow, Effinger families and others, correspondence with family members including many letters written to his mother, Katherine Taylor Effinger, as a child and photographs. Photo albums covering his entire life, including his time at Cornell as a student. Files relating to his support of Cornell include his awards and recognitions including his Hall of Fame and Foremost Benefactor inductions. Also a typescript European travel diary from a lengthy trip in 1956-1957. Also material relating to his support of the glass Blaschka Marine Invertebrate Collection. Other items relate to his work with Rotary International and the Boy Scouts of America.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ware, Barlow, 1925-2011.; Effinger family.; Cornell University -- Students.; Boy Scouts of America.; Quill and Dagger Society (Cornell University); Rotary International; Wildegg (Castle); Cornell University; Cornell University. Office of Special Projects.; Cornell University. Class of 1947.
Subjects:
Greek letter societies -- Ithaca.; Greek letter societies; Students
Places:
New York (State) -- Ithaca
Form and Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Office of Special Projects files
Series II. Photograph Albums
Series III. Personal Files Including Genealogy
Series IV. Awards, Recognitions, Ceremonies
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Office of Special Projects records
  - Alpha Delta Phi, 1958-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alpha Epsilon Phi, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chi Phi, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General fraternity information, 1975-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chi Phi, 1967-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chi Psi, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Delta Chi, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Delta Kappa Epsilon, 1960-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Delta Phi, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Delta Sigma Phi, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Delta Tau Delta, 1963-1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Group Housing funds summary, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Delta Upsilon, 1960-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Kappa Alpha, 1958-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kappa Alpha Fund, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kappa Alpha Theta, 1968-1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Kappa Delta, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kappa Sigma Group Housing Fund, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Phi Gamma Delta, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Phi Kappa Psi, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pi Kappa Phi, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Psi Upsilon, 1963-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sigma Alpha Epsilon, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - Sigma Alpha Mu, 1961-1977 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Sigma Nu, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Sigma Phi Epsilon, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Theta Delta Chi, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series II. Photograph Albums
  - Childhood photos of Ware, circa 1930 (Box 2)
    Personal photos of friends and events.
  - Photo album of Katherine Taylor Effinger, circa 1935-1940 (Box 2)
    Family album of labeled photographs of Ware as a child and other family members, friends, and travels.
  - Photo album of Katherine Taylor Effinger, circa 1935-1950 (Box 2)
    Family album of photographs of Ware as a child and other family members through his time as a Cornell student. Includes images of travels to Sierra Madre, Washington D.C. and others. Many labeled photographs of friends and family members.
  - Woodberry Forest School and Cornell University album, 1939-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes photos of student activities, Cornell Dramatic Club photos (Alex Drummond cast Ware in shows 1943-1945, campus buildings, 419 Wyckoff, Janie Caldwell, 1947 Winter ice carving contest, Cornell wrestling, 1947 graduation, Ware's mother and father, travels and family photos, Ware plot at Dale Cementery and Effinger Mausoleum in Thornrose Cemetery, Fiddle-On-Picton cabin in Clayton New York, Cornell Glee Club in Beijing China.,
  - Rotary and personal photo album, 1988-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Images of Rotary events, people, trips and personal photos. Includes photos of the Dali Lama.
  - Rotary and personal photo album, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Images of Rotary events, people, trips and personal photos. Cornell Class of 1947 reunion
  - Rotary and personal photo album, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Images of Rotary events, people, trips and personal photos.
  - Photo album of Ware's home, interior and exterior, on 524 Wyckoff Road., circa 1995 (Box 2)
  - Rotary and personal photo album, 1998-2003 (Box 2)
    Images of Rotary events, and friends. Photo of three Cornell sports announcers, Elmer "Flip" Phillips '32, Barlow Ware '47, and Arthur Mintz '71.Photo signed by President George Walker Bush. Photos of Cornell Class of 1947 reunion 2002, Ware's Athletic Hall of Fame induction.
  - Alumni affairs photo album, 2003 (Box 2)
    Possibly in honor of Ware's retirement, but also includes photos from his induction to the Cornell Athletic Hall of Fame and a letter from Ned Harkness.
  - Photo album, 2003-2006 (Box 2)
  - Takeuchi family visit photo album, December 2002 (Box 2)
  - Dedication of W. Barlow Ware Bench photo album, September 27, 2008 (Box 2)
    Dedication of stone bench outside of Teagle Hall.
  - Foremost Benefactor album, May 8, 2006 (Box 3)
    Album containing programs and photographs relating to Ware's recognition event as a foremost benefactor of Cornell University. Includes photographs of Ware, former Presidents Frank H. T. Rhodes and Dale Corson, Andy Noel and many other friends and athletic and alumni affairs staff. Photos show the presentation of the Ezra Cornell statute and Ware's inscription on the Builder's Wall. Also a number of letters with memories and thanks to Ware. Some copies of photos from early in Ware's Cornell career as well.
- Series III. Personal Files Including Genealogy
  - Biographical information, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Photos, employment history, reflections on his 50th Reunion
  - Personal files, 1946-2003 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Includes letters relating to items in his home, his Rolodex cards, correspondence, some relating to the Cornell Wrestling team, invitation letter for his induction into the Quill and Dagger Society, photo of him as Touchdown the bear and a letter from Herb Roth Sr. about Ware being the bear.
  - Barlow family genealogy, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Includes information and family trees on Brewster, Bradford, Laflin, Richmond and other surnames, descendent chart of William Henry Barlow, notes compiled by Edward Richmond Ware, History of the Episcopal Church in Sing Sing by William Henry Barlow, info on Howard Barlow, correspondence, publications.
  - Ware family genealogy, 1892-1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Information and family trees related to the Ware family. Many items relating to or from Edward Richmond Ware including baptism and birth records, military service records, pamphlet by him on the Barlow Santorium, correspondence relating to personal possessions, memorial program, correspondence relating to grave markers and deed for plots in the Dale Cemetery Association, photographs of gravestones and a map of Warecrest, the estate of E. R. Ware in Yonkers, New York, additional correspondence. Also map of Woodlawn Cemetery, info on the Elisha Ware homestead, Edward James Ware info and cabinet card, article on Henry Ware, information on the Great Bed of Ware in England.
  - Effinger and Smith family genealogy, 1985-1995 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Information and family trees related to the Effinger family. Includes correspondence from and information on Robert C. Effinger and sons. Letters to his sister Katherine and to Barlow, some not related to genealogy. Last Will and Testament of Daniel Smith of Rockingham. The Frontiersman, the publication of the Society for Descendants of Colonel John Smith. Information and correspondence relating to the opening of the Woodrow Wilson Museum at his birthplace. The museum is in the Effinger family house. Items relating to Wildegg Castle.
  - Wildegg Castle items, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Postcards, photographs, publications and correspondence relating to the castle in Switzerland. The Effinger family owned the castle.
  - Katherine Taylor Effinger items, 1921-1959 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    William Barlow Ware's wife and W. Barlow Ware Jr's mother. Includes birth and death certificates, trust indenture. Correspondence includes letters from W. B. Ware regarding their upcoming marriage, letters from doctors regarding Ware's arm. Letters from camp counsellors regarding Ware's progress, several from Camp Marienfeld in New Hampshire.
  - Letters from W. Barlow Ware Jr. to his mother, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Letters from W. Barlow Ware Jr. to his mother, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Letters from W. Barlow Ware Jr. to his mother, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Letters from W. Barlow Ware Jr. to his mother, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Letters and writings of W. Barlow Ware Jr. as a child, Circa 1935 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - European travel diary, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Typescript copies, 191 pages, of a travel diary to Europe, namely France and Italy, England and Germany are also mentioned. It is unclear the connection to Ware, though Barlow Ware is mentioned as being on the trip within, or the exact names of those involved. A cover letter is from members of the Staley family of Wellesley Hills Massachusetts. A J P. Humphreys is the likely author, probably James Patton Humphreys, who had a sister named Mary Staley. The name Brud is also mentioned frequently in the diary as is his father, Pa. Brud's brother is listed as Pat, which is probably short for Patton. Pat's wife Jane is also mentioned, this is probably Jane Schroeder Humphreys. Brud was a teacher at the Belmont Hill School Massachusetts. Pat taught at South Kent School Connecticut. Both Brud and Pat studied at the Sorbonne and much of the diary is from France. The journey begins stateside on the way to New York and a booking on the ship Maasdam.
  - Ruslan Samedov correspondence, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - John Hultgren correspondence, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Miscellany (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Includes photographs probably of Camp Marienfeld in the 1930s. Ware with Touchdown the bear, birthday cards and other correspondence and photographs. Also A Prayer for Barlow Ware dated January 22, 2006.
  - Ithaca Rotary Club News, July 1990 - July 1991 (Box 4)
    Ware's personal bound copies of Rotary News, The Rotary Club of Ithaca, New York.
  - Cornell piggy bank, MU-2498 (Box 6)
  - Small male ballet dancer statue, MU-2497 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous small items (Box 5)
    Includes Cornell seal gold cufflinks (MU-2496); various Cornell pins and fobs, many from Ware's undergraduate days, including wrestling club, manager fob, student council, Chi Phi (21351), Cayuga Society, Snoopy and Woodstock, Cornell bear, Boy Scouts of America James E. West Fellowship Award.
  - Fiddle-On-Picton cabin painting, 1975 (Box 8)
    Painting by Joe Miller of Ware's cabin in Clayton New York on the St. Lawrence River. Ware would bring various Cornell affiliated individuals for retreats here.
  - Charcoal portrait of Barlow Ware as a child (Folder 1)
    Signed by the artist, possibly G. J. Shepherd
- Series IV. Awards, Recognitions, Ceremonies
  - Awards and Recognitions (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Includes items and articles relating to Chi Phi, 1992 Tompkins County Distinguished Citizen Award, Rotary Foundation Meritorious Service Award, Boy Scouts of America Silver Beaver Award.
  - Blaschka Marine Invertebrate Collection project, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Binder of material discussing the restoration project and showing images of the unveiling celebration in Corson-Mudd Hall, November 2006.
  - Blaschka Collections, 1993-2006 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Photographs, publications, clippings and other items relating to Blaschka glass collections at Cornell and Harvard and Ware and Ware family support of the them.
  - Blaschka Glass Collection publications, 1940-1991 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Includes the book Glass Flowers in the Ware Collection by Fritz Kredel, postcards from the Corning Museum of Glass and the Cornell collections.
  - Cornell Athletic Hall of Fame Induction, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Cornell Foremost Benefactor Induction, 2005-2006 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Frank H. T. Rhodes Exemplary Alumni Service Award Induction, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Barlow Ware Bench Celebration, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Includes photographs by George Gull of the bench outside Teagle Hall placed in gratitude of Ware's love and service to Cornell.
  - Memorial Service, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Planning documents, programs, speeches, remembrances, regarding Ware's memorial service. Also photographs from Thornrose Cemetery in Staunton Virginia showing the Effinger / Ware mausoleum and Ware's marker.
    Video of the memorial service is available online here: A Celebration of the Life of Barlow Ware
  - Oversize Cornell items (Box 8)
    80th birthday card signed by many people, photo of Ware on his stone bench signed by several people, Athletic Hall of Fame certificate,
  - 70th birthday card signed by many people (Folder 1)
  - Silver tray, June 15, 1974; MU-2481 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Presented to Ware by the Chi Phi Charter House Association for devotion to the Xi chapter.
  - Boy Scouts of America Silver Beaver Award, June 18, 1980 (Box 4)
    Includes plaque and medal.
  - Unsung Hero Award Rotary District 717 plaque, 1985-1986; MU-2485 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Boy Scouts of America Baden-Powell Council Distinguished Citizen Award, 1992; MU-2499 (Box 7)
  - Horace E. Shackelton '19 Memorial Award for Track Officials, 1993; MU-2500 (Box 7)
  - Rotary Service Award plaque, 1994; MU-2487 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Ithaca Sunrise Rotary Honorary Member plaque, June 29, 1994; MU-2482 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Distinguished Service Award Rotary Foundation plaque, 1999-2000; MU-2483 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Lifetime Honorary District Governor Rotary International District 7170 plaque, 2004; MU-2484 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Rotary Foundation of Rotary International crystal dove paperweights, MU-2494-2495 (Box 5)
  - Rotary Foundation of Rotary International crystal paperweights, MU-2493 (Box 5)
  - Guardian Angel for the Ithaca Sun Rise Rotary Club plaque, MU-2486 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Beaver medal on ribbon, MU-2489 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Luggage tag, MU-2490 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Ithaca centennial medal, MU-2491 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Athletic Hall of Fame badge, MU-2492 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - The Spirit and Voice of Cornell, granite plaque with image of Ware, 2003; MU-2488 (Box 7)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
New York Times article from June 15, 1947 titled "The College Graduate-1947 Model
Signed photograph of President Livingston Farrand to Foster Coffin
Cornell blanket
Craigielea Memorial Education Fund of Chi Phi seal.
French engravings, Les deux Grands-Ducs, Un nouveau converti, and Paris enrhume by Honoré Daumier.